[SPEAKER_01]: So, there's the simile of the wild animal, but you can also think of it like a child as well.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, just kind of thinking about what it would mean to become a parent.
[SPEAKER_01]: I think whether you were planning on it or not, if you do take on that role of being a parent, your entire life becomes... the focal point becomes the fact that you're a parent.
[SPEAKER_01]: And I think that you would have to, at least to me, it seems like you would have to do that when it comes to training the mind.
[SPEAKER_01]: You have to treat it like this child.
[SPEAKER_01]: But the problem is you've been neglecting it your whole life.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then, you kind of know at any point you can just start neglecting it again.
[SPEAKER_01]: Outwardly, it wouldn't have the same consequences as if you just neglected a child.
[SPEAKER_01]: But it's much worse, actually.
[SPEAKER_01]: Much worse.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, that's just for trying to take on that practice, on that level, where, like, no, this has to be my main priority.
[SPEAKER_01]: At least to me, it seems like it's hard to just kind of click that on and stay with it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Why?
[SPEAKER_01]: It ebbs and flows with kind of bursts of inspiration, but I'm not sure if that necessarily corresponds to the actual
[SPEAKER_01]: Context of, like, really taking on the role of being a parent to the mind.
[SPEAKER_01]: I don't think that is necessarily what comes and goes with inspiration.
[SPEAKER_00]: But you mean the sense of being hateful about knowing that you're a parent?
[SPEAKER_00]: Being hateful about it, yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, so why do you think that it kind of fades?
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, because you just, you start prioritizing yourself over the child.
[SPEAKER_00]: And, and what is the necessary condition to prioritize that?
[SPEAKER_01]: I'm not sure if it would always necessarily come down to the same thing, but if just the child becomes too demanding...
[SPEAKER_00]: But, like, is it just something that happens or is it something that you fail to emphasize?
[SPEAKER_01]: Oh, yeah, it would definitely be you.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, if you take the example of a parent, like, what would they overlook because of which they would, I don't know, start going partying or doing random things that are rooted in neglect of their child?
[SPEAKER_00]: Something that applies to them, not only to the child.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, the consequences of doing that... Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, basically, what they themselves will have to put up with, as a result of neglecting the child.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, that's the only reason why you would be able to get careless.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's because it feels like you can get away with it.
[SPEAKER_00]: But, with the mind, you can't.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like, people could, hypothetically, let's say, you could transfer the ownership of your child to somebody else.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, if you reflect every single time in the past,
[SPEAKER_00]: Where you were suffering, why was it?
[SPEAKER_00]: Because of the night.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, each time you get careless, if you... like, that impulse can arise, but the thing is, if you make the effort or not, to think about how that ends.
[SPEAKER_00]: To remember all the times in the past where you were just trapped by this incessant pressure, precisely because of the same choice that you're about to make now, of saying like, no, no, it doesn't matter, I'll just go do something else and worry about this child later.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, every single time in the past, maybe it wasn't that deliberate and explicit, but that was the reason why you ended up in those
[SPEAKER_01]: And that doesn't... that doesn't necessarily mean, like, some intense experience of, like, total despair.
[SPEAKER_01]: It could just be... this is a question... Well, it hurts.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, it could just be kind of a time where you find yourself just not...
[SPEAKER_01]: Willing to do what you know you should be doing.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like, anything that feels like, I don't want to have this.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's that sense of... because, you know, there's suffering, quote-unquote suffering, that it's like... it's not really a problem.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like, you know, you're exercising, for example, and it factually hurts.
[SPEAKER_00]: But, eh... there... it's not like something that, as... as I said to say, takes over your mind, gets a grip on your mind.
[SPEAKER_00]: But then, there are other things that do.
[SPEAKER_00]: And it doesn't matter how insignificant they seem in their content.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's not the measure.
[SPEAKER_00]: The measure is that grip on the mind that they take, where it's like... it becomes the center of your experience.
[SPEAKER_00]: And even if you don't want to have it, and you want to think about something else, it just kind of sits there, keeps obsessing you.
[SPEAKER_00]: And even if it's like a minor doubt about something,
[SPEAKER_00]: It doesn't matter.
[SPEAKER_00]: The point is, like, that sense of confinement, that is the suffering.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, every time you neglect your mind and prioritize other stuff,
[SPEAKER_00]: That's what you're walking towards.
[SPEAKER_00]: That state where, like, it might be the tiniest thing, but the mind gets caught up in it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like, like a, like a, I don't know, thorn or something.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's like just trying to wriggle and left and right and it's just getting wound up more.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, that's the pain that you subject yourself to.
[SPEAKER_00]: And if you, if you, eh...
[SPEAKER_00]: Think about, like, now, before you actually get caught up in that.
[SPEAKER_00]: You see, oh, how is it now?
[SPEAKER_00]: And you realize, like, oh, yeah, I have the space to kind of think about different things.
[SPEAKER_00]: I could choose to steer direction, but you know that once you keep going there,
[SPEAKER_00]: In the direction of carelessness, that's not going to be the case anymore.
[SPEAKER_00]: If you recall your experiences in the past, like you lose... like you had... you had the control of the ship and you willingly relinquish it.
[SPEAKER_00]: And you do it because you don't clarify sufficiently how that can never be good.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because it's like you focus on these secondary benefits of whatever, failing to see that the only way that something can feel pleasant, the only way that something can feel satisfying the way you expect this thing to be, is if the mind is not wound up.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, that priority, if you actually wanted to be happy, let's say, by getting something you want,
[SPEAKER_00]: You would have to remember that that just won't come ever, unless you keep the mind in a good state.
[SPEAKER_01]: So that, that analogy you give of the, you have the steering wheel, and you do have control, but certain directions you won't?
[SPEAKER_01]: Is there anything about that, other than just your memory of having steered this way before?
[SPEAKER_00]: No, you can feel, like, you can feel it right now.
[SPEAKER_00]: Let's say you take yourself, you find a situation where you're not that pressured, which is probably going to be most of the time, if you're keeping the precepts, and you reflect, like, right now, how there is that at least relative openness.
[SPEAKER_00]: Of like, you know, there isn't something that's obsessing your mind and demanding your attention above everything else.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you actually make effort to clarify, like, why can't I maintain this state?
[SPEAKER_00]: Why is it that when something comes up and I have a view that it's better to fix it and get that content that I want,
[SPEAKER_00]: Rather than preserving the state, which is the only way that I can actually be... have the peace or satisfaction I'm looking for.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, it's that inversion, where you think that getting what you want, avoiding what you don't want, is what's going to bring you that satisfaction, whereas the only way is to maintain that state of openness of the mind.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then, doesn't matter what comes, you will not be dissatisfied.
[SPEAKER_00]: But that's something you have to reflect on, because that distortion of prioritizing getting the things or avoiding the bad things, that is beginningless.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, it's by no means obvious that the priority, the only source of happiness is actually the mind.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's not obvious at all.
[SPEAKER_00]: But as you make effort to reflect on it, then, because it is the nature of things, it will become clearer and clearer, and you will gain confidence in that fact.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, next time, when the mind pressures you with something,
[SPEAKER_00]: That, that feels like it's the end of the world if you don't get it.
[SPEAKER_00]: And you feel that constriction coming, like, starting to approach.
[SPEAKER_00]: If you have clarified that sufficiently, then you will be able to say, no, wait, this is a trap.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's the right view.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like, it's having that confidence.
[SPEAKER_00]: Not being able to doubt that, eh... you're moving in the wrong direction.
[SPEAKER_00]: There is no justification.
[SPEAKER_00]: There is no, eh... real, like, happy ending that's gonna come.
[SPEAKER_00]: From you prioritizing anything over the mind.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because whatever you're prioritizing, you are still prioritizing the mind, just wrongly.
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, it comes first.
[SPEAKER_00]: It still comes first.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, it's like, it's the...
[SPEAKER_00]: Imagine you think that you can experience things directly, but there's always that thing in between.
[SPEAKER_00]: You think that you...
[SPEAKER_00]: I can just... That's actually a perfect way of describing the distortion.
[SPEAKER_00]: You think I can just have this thing I want, and just because I have it, I will be happy.
[SPEAKER_00]: But you have absolutely no access.
[SPEAKER_00]: There is not a single inch of that thing that you can touch, except through the mind.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, that's why it's completely... it makes absolutely no sense.
[SPEAKER_00]: To shift that order, because even if it feels like it's like a... like it can only ever be an ignorant perception.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, that's why the ignorance is beginningless.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like, it makes absolutely no sense.
[SPEAKER_00]: If it was something that you had decided to start thinking, you couldn't have, because it just doesn't make sense.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then, also, you can take the times when things weren't the way you wanted, but the mind was relatively open, let's say, and you can see, oh yes, actually, like, this is a direct demonstration of how it is actually the craving that's the problem.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because there's always imperfections, always things that are not as ideal.
[SPEAKER_00]: And many of those times, there will be that mind in between that is actually fine with it.
[SPEAKER_00]: And you can see, oh, yeah, actually, this wasn't as much of a problem as it would have been if the mind was pressured.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because it can be hard to see that literally anything that you're... even if it's like you're worried about the practice and whether you'll succeed and make progress and whatnot, that's all still kind of obviously...
[SPEAKER_01]: The significance of that is kind of defined by how the mind regards it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then, you would... that's how you would be misconceiving the practice.
[SPEAKER_00]: You would be thinking like, oh, yeah, it's this stuff that I have to do.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's about this thing.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, whatever... whatever it happens to be, it's this stuff over there.
[SPEAKER_00]: Whereas, eh... it's... the practice is to purify that mind through which you're thinking about the practice.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, to... to tame that... you could say... tame the pain.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's like that sutta where it's the former prince who's out in the forest saying, oh, this is happiness, this is bliss.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like... Yeah, yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: If your mind
[SPEAKER_01]: was just completely chill with the fact that there are leopards and panthers that might eat you the next second.
[SPEAKER_01]: It wouldn't be a problem.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because your mind is not exactly having issues with it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, in a way, it's obvious.
[SPEAKER_00]: But see, when it's kind of in the flesh,
[SPEAKER_00]: And there's that active impulse to prioritize the situation.
[SPEAKER_00]: You kind of go with it.
[SPEAKER_00]: You let the emphasis drift away.
[SPEAKER_00]: Whereas, if you, like, actually made the effort to think about it, when it's in those situations, it's kind of going to be against the grain.
[SPEAKER_00]: You're gonna have to be kind of fighting against that irrational impulse to blame the circumstances.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's what people don't do.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like, it makes sense to them that, yes, to most people, I'm sure, that the mind is the reason why they're happy or sad.
[SPEAKER_00]: But let's say you're in the middle of an argument that feels like extremely important and it's like the end of the world if it doesn't go the way you want.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then you don't want to think about the fact that it's actually the mind that makes things unpleasant, because it won't allow you to to double down in this investment the way you want to.
[SPEAKER_00]: It would kind of make the whole thing seem pointless.
[SPEAKER_00]: And it is.
[SPEAKER_00]: But that's the whole point.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like, you have to make the effort to think about it, because this ignorance is not just like an abstract state.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's an impulse.
[SPEAKER_00]: You don't want to think about the way things are.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's like when you're... Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Kind of like you're saying the argument.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like when you're in an argument with somebody and you realize your point is wrong, but you don't want to... Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: ...admit it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: It seems like...
[SPEAKER_01]: Having the correct approach to the mind is like constantly being wrong in an argument that you're really invested in winning.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then having to admit that you have to admit it.
[SPEAKER_01]: I remember in lay life, somebody wanted to, like, quit smoking and was asking about it.
[SPEAKER_01]: And a friend had said, like, the most important thing is to let yourself feel bad about it if you do it.
[SPEAKER_01]: You're not going to stop smoking overnight, unless you're, you know, really serious and whatnot.
[SPEAKER_01]: But, kind of in the meantime, you have to admit to yourself that it's not good, when you are making the decision to do it.
[SPEAKER_01]: And, in a way, that's kind of...
[SPEAKER_01]: Coming at the root, which it's always like, oh, well, it's okay this time.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's always going to manifest that way.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, because it's that sense of not wanting to feel guilty about something that is actually against your welfare.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's quite similar, yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like, not wanting to feel the burden of, um, I shouldn't be giving in to this craving.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like, just even before you decide, like, I'm actually not going to give in,
[SPEAKER_00]: Just the fact of being aware that it's bad to give in.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, that's why delusion is actually the most fundamental of all the three defilements.
[SPEAKER_00]: Without delusion, the other ones cannot exist.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because it's the delusion that allows you to keep... like it's because you already decided to not see it as a problem, that you can act out in in the form of greed or in the form of aversion.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then, obviously, the times where you're doing something and you're like, I shouldn't be doing this, it's either, A. it's not actually a problem and you're kind of overdoing it, or you just haven't seen that it's a problem clearly enough.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, how do you see that whether it's a problem or not, when in those cases where it might be ambiguous?
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, ask, where is the pressure?
[SPEAKER_00]: Is the pressure in continuing to do the thing or is the pressure in me thinking about the stuff that I shouldn't be doing and the restraint and the kind of renunciation or whatever?
[SPEAKER_00]: If the pressure is in the second one,
[SPEAKER_00]: Then, it probably isn't the problem.
[SPEAKER_00]: You just kind of... your mind just wants to find an outlet for that pressure of restlessness.
[SPEAKER_00]: Something that it can blame for like, no, I'm just restless and I shouldn't be acting out of that restlessness.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, see, that's another case where you would be prioritizing something over the mind.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like, you might have all these ideas of sense of duty that, oh, I should be engaging in these behaviors and avoiding these other ones, as a goal for, like, for its own sake.
[SPEAKER_00]: And you don't see that, actually, why would I be doing that?
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, the only answer is because I want to tame my mind.
[SPEAKER_00]: Okay, so, is that actually going to tame my mind?
[SPEAKER_00]: Like, is that detracting from pressures that my mind has?
[SPEAKER_00]: Or is that the pressure that my mind has?
[SPEAKER_01]: If you overlook that context of why you're doing it, like, of, like, the point of this is training the mind... Yeah, then that's, that's the whole sīla bhātta-paramāsa.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, you're just falling into, like, virtue for virtue's sake.
[SPEAKER_00]: Even if it's the right behavior, and the right abstaining, and the right restraint, the fact that you're overlooking why you have to do it, makes it inaccurate.
[SPEAKER_01]: And it won't always be the right restraint, if it's...
[SPEAKER_01]: Sorry?
[SPEAKER_01]: It won't always be the right restraint, if you're not keeping that priority.
[SPEAKER_00]: No, like... Because you will fall into, like, this... Yeah, no, I meant in the sense of, like, let's say, the thing arises as if... because, obviously, you don't have an outside point of view.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, to you, it will arise as if, like, oh, yes, this is an intention to keep the precepts, for example.
[SPEAKER_00]: An intention to factually do what I have to do.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, it will feel like it is the right restraint.
[SPEAKER_00]: Even if afterwards you can say like, yeah, that was kind of distorted to some extent because of the pressure.
[SPEAKER_00]: To you, that is the direction of the restraint.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, eh... you don't try to deny that.
[SPEAKER_00]: You just realize like, wait, no, but...
[SPEAKER_00]: I'm not doing this because after I do this, some magical thing will happen and the pieces will come together or something.
[SPEAKER_00]: The only reason that this makes... that there is any point to this is because, well, when the mind has greed, the mind must not be allowed to act out of greed.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, have I seen the greed that I'm trying to get rid of?
[SPEAKER_00]: Because, yeah, maybe those behaviors will restrain something.
[SPEAKER_00]: Nobody says they won't, but it will not actually succeed
[SPEAKER_00]: And it will not actually tame those defilements, unless you're aware of what defilements you're trying to get rid of, by, let's say, abstaining by, you know, those, all those suttas, like...
[SPEAKER_00]: He would reflect, reflect according to the origin, reflect the yoniso,
[SPEAKER_00]: And with that, he would eat only for the sake of sustaining this body.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, like, you're not just taking on a sense of duty of, oh, you shouldn't eat too much because, you know, that's bad for the practice.
[SPEAKER_00]: You reflect yoniso to see, like, oh, I actually... you can see
[SPEAKER_00]: The pressure to eat for its own sake.
[SPEAKER_00]: You can see the pressure to find safety in food.
[SPEAKER_00]: You can see the pressure to just enjoy taste.
[SPEAKER_00]: And to that extent, you contradict it by eating only for the sake of the maintenance of this body.
[SPEAKER_00]: Which means, in turn,
[SPEAKER_00]: That if there is no pressure to, like, enjoy the taste for its own sake and delight in that, then you don't need to, like, push through this reflection.
[SPEAKER_00]: You just stay aware that there is no greed right now, for example.
[SPEAKER_00]: There's that whole sutta where the Buddha says, a monk who is wise engages in difficult practice when he sees that there is something to wear away through that difficult practice.
[SPEAKER_00]: When that thing has worn away, he does not engage in difficult practice anymore.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, no, like, universal dhūtaṅga that you do forever because it's like, you know, a good... it's good, period.
[SPEAKER_00]: If you can't explain it, then you're probably doing for the wrong reason.
[SPEAKER_01]: But you're just saying that even in reference to a reflection.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, because it is a kind of, well, burden that you're subjecting yourself to.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, there has to be a reason.
[SPEAKER_00]: There has to be an awareness of there is a defilement that I'm trying to restrain with this.
[SPEAKER_00]: I'm not just doing it because you want to do it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because then, that could be the restlessness.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then, you're putting the mind second.
[SPEAKER_01]: And really, you would only do it if you didn't want to.
[SPEAKER_01]: Basically, yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: But there wouldn't be a sense of duty about something like that.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: It would be something where you're like...
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, the pressure would be to go with the flow of, let's say, enjoying the taste, and you're going in the opposite direction.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, that's the whole point of that phrase, against the grain.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, if the grain is like, I want to enjoy this, well, against the grain is to reflect on why I shouldn't enjoy this, or reflect on something that at least puts that enjoyment second and doesn't allow me to act towards it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Then, if the grain is like... yeah, I'm not even thinking about the taste of the food.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like, it's not even crossing my mind.
[SPEAKER_00]: But the obsession now is, I must engage in this reflection.
[SPEAKER_00]: Then, if you do that now, that's with the grain.
[SPEAKER_01]: That means you've lost sight of what this whole restraint is supposed to be about.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, and you're not seeing the mind anymore, yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you will actually feel the tug of that defilement if you don't reflect.
[SPEAKER_00]: You see, like, the mind wants to find some other duty to latch on to, some other kind of way to feel safe through that constant activity.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then, your reflection is why you shouldn't engage in that.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's now against the grain.